Bachar Bouazza

L +1 (514) 224-1942 • ☑ bachar.bouazza@gmail.com

Profile

Good working experience with functional and object oriented programming languages such as Python, R, C/C++. Sound knowledge of applied mathematics in solving business and scientific problems. Ability to translate complex mathematical blueprints, models, into equivalent computer programs.

Professional Experience

Self Employed Montreal, Quebec,

Analytics/Research Scientist

2013-today

My research project consists on integrating 3 domaines of knowledge: management science, applied mathematics, and computer science. The following topics where carefully studied and analyzed:

- o Tensor calculus (multidimensional data representation), machine learning models review, Stochastic processes, Levy processes, Probability theory, Stochastic differential equations(SDE), multivariate statistical analysis, Monte Carlo simulation
- Supply chaine management systems, Entreprise resource planning (ERP)
- o Design patterns, Architectural patterns, Archetype patterns and their applications to solve complex problems.
- \circ C++/C, Python and R languages, TensorFlow and neural networks
- Market models, Portfolio theory, Fixed income models, Derivative analytics, Financial risk measures

Markit Analytics Calgary, Alberta

Software developer

2012-2013

- Tied together numerical simulation and mathematically complex report generation
- Performed I/O and computation on very large data sets basically using HDF data model
- Optimized time and memory performance of parallel, distributed portfolio calculation runs.
- Designed and Implemented the credit risk measure CVA/DVA using appropriate market curves to estimate the probability of default of the counter-party
- Added new features to account for specific exposures in the VaR (Value at Risk) framework

AESO (Alberta Electric System Operator)

Calgary, Alberta

Software developer

2010-2012

- o Designed and maintained functional, performance, stress and endurance tests
- Developed a simulation model in Java, using Tibco and activeMQ event management systems technologies, to simulate events in the system, used for stress tests
- o Lead regular interaction between the performance testing team and the infrastructure services team supporting the platforms
- Initiated a comparative study of economic dispatching models as used in the energy markets

MatchMine, Kraft Group

Boston, MA, USA

Quantitative developer

2007-2009

- Developed a multidimensional content model for document classification and clustering purpose
- o Bayesian, neural networks, and vector support machine models research
- Proposed state of the art models to enhance content scoring: kernel methods, Bayesian models
- o Designed and implemented, in Java, a multithreaded, context-directed web crawler

Pfizer Inc Groton, CT, USA

Consultant 2005–2007

- Parallelized large computational chemistry applications using Matlab, Python, R, PVM, MPI
- o Performed software installation and configuration on the GRID
- Acted as technical interface between different users of the GRID
- o Automated manual back-office processing through scripting and automation engine
- o Improved the performance of straight-through processing by adding caching mechanisms

Gulf University for Science and Technology

Kuwait, Kuwait

Assistant professor

2002-2005

- o Thought university grad computer science courses: Java/C++/C languages, relational database management systems, operating systems, and software design
- Mentored and supervised students in their final projects

Hewlett-Packard Manalapan, NJ, USA

Software Engineer

1999-2002

- o Maintained representation of HP in UNIX Base Working Group and Linux Standard Base
- Coordinated the UNIX branding process: interacting with many groups to handle issues, fixing UNIX bugs, continuous integration test-suits planning and reporting
- \circ Designed and implemented a console management facility, in Posix C/C++ and Java, to monitor a park of alpha server cluster machines

Statistics Canada Ottawa, Ontario

Programmer/Analyst

1996-1999

- Implemented statistical imputation algorithms to handle outliers and missing data in survey data sets in UNIX environment
- o Designed and implemented Oracle stored procedures and tables
- Assumed DBA responsibilities
- Designed and developed a client/server application to automate the survey workflow process, in Java/Oracle

Skills

Programming: C/C++, boost, Java, Python (NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib), R, Unix Scripting

Software Methodologies: Test Driven Design, UML, Domaine/Design Patterns, Agile

Operating Systems: Linux, UNIX, Windows

Database systems: Oracle, MySQL, SQL Servers

Quantitative Methods: Multivariate statistical analysis models, stochastic processes, Monte Carlo

methods, Multidimensional Calculus, Time series analysis, optimization

Education

Université De Montréal Montreal, Canada

Masters's degree 1998

Computer Science

Université Laval Québec, Canada

MBA, Master's in Business Administration

Decision Systems (Operational Research)

Université Mohammed V Rabat, Morocco

Master Mathematics 1991

Functional Analysis

1994

Languages

English: Very good **French**: Very good

Publications

1998: B. F. Lamond et B. Bachar: Une étude numérique de la discrétisation des apports aléatoires pour un réservoir non saisonnier. INFOR 36, pp. 247-260.